Stuart W. Franklin Papers VHP2006/25
CCSU Veterans History Project
Stuart Franklin Papers
Bulk, 1942-1945
1942 - 1945, 2004, 2007
VHP2006/25
CCSU Veterans History Project
100.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details experience of Stuart W. Franklin as he served as a mechanic for the Quartermaster Truck Company of U.S. Army during World War II in Europe. The collection includes personal military records, World War II era publications, and photographs.
Franklin, Stuart W., (Stuart Whilney), 1914 - 2007
Biographical/Historical note
Stuart W. Franklin enlisted in the United States Army in 1942. He had first applied for officer candidate school; however, he was called into active duty in September of 1942 after failing the test. He was sent to Camp Lee, Va. for basic training, and was simultaneously trained as a mechanic for the quartermaster corps. He was transferred to North Carolina, where he was trained to work on truck engines, and he became a mechanic with the 135th Quartermaster Truck Company. On February 14, 1944 he shipped overseas aboard the H.M.S. Queen Mary with more than 20, 000 other troops. They landed in Glasgow, Scotland, but because they did not have trucks to enter France with yet, they stayed for a time outside of London. Franklin and a squad of six men were staying outside London when the last of the large bomb raids by Germany took place. The house the soldiers were in had a bomb hit the second floor, but the men all remained unharmed. Franklin was issued a truck with a machine gun mount and 50 caliber machine gun the day after the raid, and his unit was then sent over to France. In France, he was responsible for the maintenance of the truck, and hauling supplies to other units. The 135th Quartermaster Truck Unit was moved to Wiesbaden, Germany, just before the war was declared over. Franklin remained in Wiesbaden until November of 1945, when he again sailed on the Queen Mary to return home. He was discharged in December of 1945, and he returned home to his wife in Putnam, Ct. where he worked in wholesale plumbing until his retirement.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
United States. Army. Quartermaster Truck Company, 135th .; United States. Army.; England; Fort Lee (Va.); Fort Pickett (Va.); France; Queen Mary (Steamship); United Service Organizations (U.S.); Vehicles, Military; Wiesbaden (Germany); World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Europe; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/25.I
  - Berth card aboard the H.M.S. Queen Mary going overseas, circa 1944; VHP2006/25.I.01
  - Stuart Franklin’s Motor Vehicle Operator’s Permit, Aug. 23, 1943; VHP2006/25.I.02
  - Interview synopsis, Dec. 28, 2004; VHP2006/25.I.03
  - Interview transcript, Dec. 28, 2004; VHP2006/25.I.04
- Series II: Military Documents, VHP2006/25.II
  - Application for family allowance form, 1942; VHP2006/25.II.01; 2.0 Digital objects
  - Soldier's Individual Pay Record, 1942; VHP2006/25.II.02; 4.0 Digital objects
  - List of the 135th Quartermaster Truck Company Members, 1945; VHP2006/25.II.03; 2.0 Digital objects
- Series III: Publications, VHP2006/25.III
  - American Red Cross Map of London, circa 1940s; VHP2006/25.III.01; 8.0 Digital objects
  - Rollin Home: on board H.M.S. Queen Mary journal, Nov. 26, 1945; VHP2006/25.III.02; 8.0 Digital objects
  - Connecticut Men of the United States Army: Demobilization, fort Devens, MA, Dec. 2, 1945; VHP2006/25.III.03; 11.0 Digital objects
- Series IV: Multi-Media, VHP2006/25.IV
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2006/25.IV
    - Stuart Franklin military photo, 1942; VHP2006/25.IV.1
    - Members of 135th Truck Company. Kershaw, NC, May 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.2
      Scope and Contents note
      Soldier in center is Hastings, soldier to the right is from TX, Victor Juarez has back to camera
    - Motor Sgt. repairing one of the truck flat tire during maneuvers. Kershaw, NC, May 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.3
    - Cook’s truck at Company headquarters during maneuvers. Kershaw, NC, May 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.4
    - Members of 135th Quartermaster Truck Company at Camp McCall, NC, May 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.5
      L– R, Sgt. Baker, PFC Connally, Unknown, First Sgt. Freemole, Corp. St. Laurent, and Private Hastings
    - Corporal Riley at Camp McCall, NC, May 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.6
    - Members of 135th Quartermaster Truck Company. Camp McCall, NC, May 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.7
      L-R: Baker, St. Laurent, Hastings, Corp. Mandeville of Pascoag, RI with back to camera
    - 2nd Lt. Peck at Camp McCall, NC, May 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.8
    - Corporal St. Laurent (left) and Sgt. Bajeck. Camp McCall, NC, 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.9
    - Stuart Franklin at Camp McCall, NC, 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.10
    - PFC Stuart Franklin. Camp McCall, NC, June 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.11
    - Soldiers playing cards. Camp McCall, NC, June 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.12
    - Paratroopers getting ready to jump. Camp McCall, NC, July 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.13
    - Paratrooper Training. Camp McCall, NC, July 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.14
    - Landed Paratrooper lying down. Camp McCall, NC, July 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.15
    - Paratrooper Training. Camp McCall, NC, July 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.16
    - Unknown soldier and Stuart Franklin (right) Camp McCall, NC, July 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.17
    - From L—R: Tazinski, unknown, and Skovuland. Camp McCall, NC, July 1943; VHP2006/25.IV.18
    - Stuart Franklin at Camp McCall, NC, January 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.19
    - Formal Retreat at Altrincham, Cheshire County, England, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.20
    - “End of Day” Retreat at Altrincham, England, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.21
    - Gaal writing a letter. England, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.22
    - Entrance to Hyde Park, England, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.23
    - Hyde Park, England with “Soap Boxer”, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.24
    - Crossing from England to France on Liberty Ship, August 3, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.25
    - View from hotel window. Avenue des Champs-Élysées, Paris, France, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.26
    - Arch de Triomphe, Paris, France, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.27
    - View of Paris with The Eiffel Tower in center background, France, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.28
    - Covered machine gun with Arc de Triomphe in background. Paris, France, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.29
    - Convoy in Paris, France, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.30
    - unknown soldiers, France, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.31
    - Broken German tank, France, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.32
    - German POWs cleaning road. Cross Road at Pierriers, France, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.33
    - German POWs cleaning road. Pierriers, France, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.34
    - An American convoy in a Normandy Town, France, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.35
    - U.S. truck and trailer, France, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.36
    - Crap game in progress, France, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.37
      Milstead is at far left Facing camera left to right are Mueller, unknown, Schwab, and Vasinosky
    - Rhine River, Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.38
      Stuart Franklin in foreground, to his right is Rejcek (back) and Imph (in a squatting position) A local child is in the background.
    - Stuart Franklin’s bed roll and duffle bag in a truck, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.39
      Stuart would sleep in bed of his 2 1/2 ton, 6X6 truck when on maneuvers. “somewhere in Europe”
    - Stuart Franklin manning machine gun in a first convoy to Wiesbaden, Germany, April 1945; VHP2006/25.IV.40
    - Stuart Franklin doing laundry at Wiesbaden, Biebrich, Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.41
    - The “wet wash” laundry equipment captured from the Germans. Biebrich, Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.42
    - Convoy getting ready to leave Biebrich, Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.43
      L-R, Geoffrey Gorican, Lasascio, and Avants
    - Truck convoy getting ready for detail. Trucks parked in Biebrich, Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.44
    - U. S. Barracks in Biebrich, Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.45
    - Main building at headquarters and softball field. Biebrich, Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.46
      George Freemole on the left with First Sgt. Bernie Pearce
    - Headquarters main building. Wiesbaden, Biebrich, Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.47
    - 1st Sgt. Freemole holding Unit Meritorious Service Award. Headquarters in Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.48
    - Autobahn twenty miles south of Nuremberg, Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.49
    - Backside of Red Cross Club. Wiesbaden, Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.50
    - Fort used by U.S. Information Division for quarters. Wurzburg, Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.51
    - Stuart Franklin (right) with an unknown soldier. Biebrich, Germany, 1944; VHP2006/25.IV.52
    - Good neighbor policy with young Germans, July 1945; VHP2006/25.IV.53
      Stuart Franklin and his Lieutenant slept by this stream. Bavarian Alps can be seen in the background.
    - Stuart Franklin in 2007, VHP2006/25.IV.54
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2006/25.IVb
    - Oral history interivew with Stuart Franklin, Dec. 28, 2004; VHP2006/25.IVb.1; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2006/25, Box VHP Interview 2006)